Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New York Public Library
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New York Public Library
N/A
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892
Bucke, R.M.
Burroughs, John
W. T. H. Howe; Bliss Perry; Albert A. Berg; Owen D. Young
poetry prose Nearly 35 Whitman manuscripts, or manuscript fragments, and 13 manuscripts relating to Whitman. In addition, there are approximately 200 ALS and ANS; 150 postal cards; 70 letters written to Whitman; and 30 letters regarding him.
New York Public Library New York Public Library Humanities and Social Sciences Library Room 320 5th Avenue and 42nd Street New York, NY 10018-2788
The collection was processed by Sarah Dickson and John Gordan, primarily in 1941. This catalog was created from a text originally generated in 1998, converted to EAD-SGML by Terry Catapano in May 2000, and obtained by the Walt Whitman Archive. The inventory for the collection was created by Diana Burnham in 2000.
Restrictions:
Access to the collection is restricted to qualified scholars and researchers through the Office of Special Collections, Room 316, Humanites and Social Sciences Library, New York Public Library. Requests for reproduction and/or permission to quote must be made in writing to the Curator and be accompanied by Estate permission.
Alternative Format:
Digital images of some items are available in the "Manuscripts" section of the Archive.
Scope and Content
The Berg Collection's letters and manuscripts by Walt Whitman cover the years 1854 to 1891, with a small amount of material as yet undated. Strengths of the collection include nearly 30 manuscript poems or poem fragments and Whitman's autograph revision of the Analysis of Poems by Dr. R. Bucke. This essay was written for Bucke's authorized biography (Walt Whitman, 1883) and Whitman's extensive revisions were incorporated before publication. The correspondence includes two longer runs, one to William O' Connor and the other to his wife, Ellen O'Connor. The O'Connors were active in a number of social causes, as well as being devoted advocates of Whitman and his writing. William O'Connor, author of The Good Gray Poet (1866), was one of Whitman's closest friends until an argument in 1873 caused a break in their friendship.
Others who figure prominently in the Berg Collection's Whitman materials include John Burroughs (1837-1921), nature writer, literary critic, and author of Notes on Walt Whitman as Poet and Person (1867); Peter Doyle and Harry Stafford, young friends of Whitman's; and Richard Maurice Bucke (1837-1902), Whitman's authorized biographer, friend and literary executor. In addition to writing Walt Whitman (1883) and Walt Whitman, Man and Poet (1898), Bucke co-edited with Horace Traubel and Thomas Harned The Complete Writings (1902).
This catalog includes item-level descriptions of only those items deemed poetry or prose manuscripts.
Subjects
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892--Manuscripts; Poets, American--19th century
Item List
- As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free, around 1872; nyp.00003; xxx.00267; poetry 14 leaves handwritten (Box Manuscript box.)
  A copy of As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free with directions to the printer, as returned to Whitman from the printing office. As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free was first published in the New York Herald on 26 June 1872. Afterward the poem was published with seven others in a pamphlet, As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free (1872). It was later included as a supplement bound with Two Rivulets (1876). Later, Whitman changed the title to Thou Mother with Thy Equal Brood, added a new opening stanza, made additional revisions, and incorporated the poem into Leaves of Grass (1881–82). This manuscript was presented by the author to Richard J. Hinton, who in turn presented it to J. H. Johnston.
- Broadway, 1861. | [I too am drawn] | [I have lived], around 1861; nyp.00004; xxx.00666; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box Oversized (+).)
  Lightly revised handwritten copy of a poem titled Broadway, 1861, which is unrelated to the poem Broadway that Whitman published in the New York Herald in 1888. Harold W. Blodgett and Sculley Bradley note the similarity of Broadway, 1861 to the opening poem of Drum-Taps, First O Songs for a Prelude, particularly "in its theme of the arousing of the energies of the great city—and of the nation—to the war." They also note this similarity in the two poems composed on the reverse of this leaf, "I Too Am Drawn.. ." and "I Have Lived.. ."
- A Child's Reminiscence, about 1859; nyp.00005; xxx.00131; poetry 19 leaves handwritten (Box Cased.)
  Printer's copy of the poem A Child's Reminiscence, which appeared in the New-York Saturday Press on 24 December 1859. This poem later appeared as A Word Out of the Sea in Leaves of Grass (1860); as Out of the Cradle Endlessly Rocking in Sea-Shore Memories, Passage to India (1871); and finally in Sea Drift, Leaves of Grass (1881–82).
- content to the ground, between 1845 and 1860; nyp.00040; xxx.00664; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A list of words beginning with "the blacksmith's shop" and "the brewery" that could be related to a poem. The phrase "content to the ground" is probably tied to some other text from another scrap, since it is visually distinct from the other words on this leaf.
- The Dead Emperor, about 1888; nyp.00006; xxx.00370; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Printer's copy of the poem The Dead Emperor, which was first published in the New York Herald on 10 March 1888 and later reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass ( 1888 ). The poem mourns the death of Emperor William I of Germany on 9 March 1888, and the Herald of 10 March contained details of his final hours as well as Whitman's poem.
- A Death-Sonnet for Custer, about 1876; nyp.00007; xxx.00285; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Printer's copy of the poem A Death-Sonnet for Custer with instructions to preserve the manuscript in its current form for Bayard Taylor. A Death-Sonnet for Custer first appeared in the New York Daily Tribune on 10 July 1876. It was then reprinted as From Far Dakotas Cañons in Leaves of Grass (1881–82).
- Go, said his Soul to a Poet., 1870-1874; nyp.00013; xxx.00596; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A rough draft, heavily revised, of a poem titled Go, said his Soul to a Poet, which was first published in A Christmas Garland of Prose and Verse in the December 25, 1874 issue of the New York Daily Graphic and later used, without title, as the title-page epigraph for Leaves of Grass.
- [growing] | Poems, about 1859; nyp.00014; xxx.00087; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Five lines of the poem I Saw in Louisiana a Live Oak Growing. This poem is part of the Calamus cluster, which Whitman began assembling in the summer of 1859. The reverse features a note by the poet to himself, describing the poems as "A Cluster of Poems, Sonnets expressing the thoughts, pictures, aspirations &c Fit to be perused during the days of the approach of Death."
- I last winter observed the snow, nyp.00022; xxx.00669; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Two untitled lines of poetry. Sculley Bradley and Harold W. Blodgett suggest that the mention of a "wild-drake" may connect this scrap to the line about a "wood-drake" in what became section 13 of Song of Myself (line 237 in the Deathbed Edition). However, that connection seems tenuous, as nothing else about the lines in this scrap suggest a connection to Song of Myself.
- Interpolation Sounds, about 1891; nyp.00059; xxx.00393; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box Manuscript box.)
  Fair copy draft of the poem Interpolation Sounds. This poem first appeared without a title in the New York Herald four days after Whitman's short prose tribute to General Philip K. Sheridan, a Union general during the Civil War. It was reprinted in Good-Bye My Fancy in 1891, with the additional note: "General Sheridan was buried at the Cathedral, Washington, D.C. August, 1888, with all the pomp, music and ceremonies of the Roman Catholic service."
- [? A laurel wreath], about 1888; nyp.00053; xxx.00314; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box Oversized (+).)
  Heavily revised draft of the poem To Those Who've Fail'd. The poem was published in the New York Herald on 27 January 1888 and later reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass (1888).
- Leaves Supervenio, nyp.00038; xxx.00670; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Two trial titles, "Leaves Supervenio" and "Leaves Supervened." As Edward F. Grier writes, these titles may "refer to WW's plans about 1870 to compose a new volume of poetry."
- [or, Halcyon Days] | Fancies at Navesink, around 1888; nyp.00043; xxx.00329; xxx.00330; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Draft for a title page, beginning "or Halycon days," with a note at the head "for title page to supplement of L of G not Nov. Boughs." The verso appears to have been a previous title page draft for Fancies at Navesink. Halcyon Days first appeared in the New York Herald on 29 January 1888, and was reprinted in the Sands at Seventy Annex to Leaves of Grass (1888).
- The Pallid Wreath, 1891; nyp.00074; xxx.00386; poetry 2 leaves handwritten
  Draft of the poem The Pallid Wreath, which was published in the Critic 18 (10 January 1891) and reprinted in Good-Bye My Fancy (1891). The original envelope containing the draft and comments to the editor of the Critic is included.
- [To pass existence], about 1855; nyp.00052; xxx.00674; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  On one side of this scrap is a single unidentified line of poetry, heavily revised. On the other side are two lines, revised, also unidentified.
- Poem of the Ancient, probably before 1867; nyp.00039; xxx.00676; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Notes toward a poem on the "earth," "heavens," and "the Ancient." On the verso are some numbers and calculations.
- Sea Winrows, between 1860 and 1881; nyp.00033; xxx.00132; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A list of words probably related to the poem As I Ebb'd with the Ocean of Life, originally published as Bardic Symbols in the Atlantic Monthly 5 (April 1860). The final version of the poem was published in Leaves of Grass (1881-82). The verso features the words "Sands and Drifts."
- The Sobbing of the Bells, 1881; nyp.00075; xxx.00302; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box Cased.)
  Draft fragment of the poem The Sobbing of the Bells, unsigned and dated midnight, Sept. 19-20, 1881. Included at the top of the manuscript is a note to Mr. Clarke regarding the setup and proof. The poem treats the death of President James Garfield and was first published in the Boston Daily Globe on September 27, 1881.
- Song of the Universal, 1874; nyp.00076; xxx.00123; poetry 13 leaves handwritten
  Draft of the poem The Song of the Universal, which first appeared simultaneously in The New York Evening Post and The New York Daily Graphic on 17 June 1874. It was later reprinted in the New York World on 19 June 1874, in the Camden New Republic on 20 June 1874, and in Two Rivulets (1876).
- Tar, turpentine, shingles, about 1860; nyp.00037; xxx.00684; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Notes, probably toward a poem, mentioning building materials from North Carolina, slaves driving carts, a lumber boat, and a pack of dogs ready for a slave hunt.
- [Two little buds], unknown; nyp.00044; xxx.00685; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A note consisting of four lines, possibly written toward a poem, that present the metaphor of "two little human buds" prematurely taken from the earth to bloom in "God's immortal garden." The relationship between this draft and Whitman's published poetry is unknown.
- Warble for Lilac-Time, 1870-1881; nyp.00047; xxx.00234; poetry 4 leaves handwritten
  Fair copy draft of the poem Warble for Lilac-Time, first published in the Galaxy 9 (May 1870). Whitman revised the poem for reprinting in Passage to India (1871), in the New York Daily Graphic (12 May 1873), in the group Passage to India of Leaves of Grass (1872) and Two Rivulets (1876), and in its present form in Leaves of Grass (1881-82).
- We Are, 1850-1860; nyp.00025; xxx.00687; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Two lines of poetry with an unknown relation to Whitman's published work.
- Yonnondio, 1887-1888; nyp.00049; xxx.00350; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Heavily revised draft of the poem Yonnondio, which first appeared in the Critic 11 (26 November 1887). It was reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass (1888).
- You lingering sparse leaves of me., about 1887; nyp.00050; xxx.00368; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Lightly revised draft of the poem You lingering sparse leaves of me, first published in Lippincott's Magazine 40 (November 1887) with three other poems, under the title November Boughs. It was then reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass (1888).
- You tokens diminute and lorn, about 1887; nyp.00051; xxx.00368; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Three lines of a draft of You lingering sparse leaves of me, first published in Lippincott's Magazine 40 (November 1887) with three other poems, under the title November Boughs. It was then reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass (1888).
- [A youth beloved by all], 1865-1885; nyp.00045; xxx.00688; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Two lines written on the top of a piece of letter-head stationery of the Attorney General's Office.
- [Iron works], 1855–1856; nyp.00021; xxx.00119; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Prose notes and poetic lines that relate to A Song for Occupations, which first appeared in the 1856 edition of Leaves of Grass, under the title Poem of the Daily Work of the Workmen and Workwomen of These States. The title of this poem shifted throughout the editions of Leaves of Grass, and included the following variants: Chants Democratic, The Workingmen, and Carol of Occupations. Whitman finally settled on the title, A Song for Occupations, in the 1881–1882 edition. The line, "The forge-fires in the mountains...the men around, feeling the melt with huge crowbars" appeared slightly revised in both early and late versions of this poem. Other ideas detailed in the prose portion of this manuscript can be found in this poem; however, the connection of this manuscript to Whitman's published prose work is unclear.
- [wider than the west], 1850–1855; nyp.00510; xxx.00111; xxx.00048; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A draft fragment containing phrases and poetic lines, which were revised and used in different poems of Leaves of Grass. "The orbed opening of whose mouth," struck through on this manuscript, is suggestive of a line which appeared in the poem ultimately called Song of Myself: "The orbic flex of his mouth is pouring and filling me full." The line which reads, "Nature is rude at first—but once begun never tires" was used slightly altered in the 1856 edition of Leaves of Grass, under the title Poem of the Road (Whitman revised the title to Song of the Open Road in the 1867 edition). On the verso of this manuscript is a prose fragment on the subject of knowledge and learning. It is unclear how this manuscript may relate to Whitman's published prose writings.
- [222—No.—(? Have you supplied], 1850-1860; nyp.00028; xxx.00839; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Two scraps of paper, pasted together to form one leaf. The relation of this manuscript to Whitman's published work is unclear.
- Walt Whitman's birthday, 1884; nyp.00046; xxx.00840; prose 3 leaves handwritten
  A fair copy of Walt Whitman's Birthday, a short article that appeared in the 31 May 1884 issue of the Philadelphia Times.
- [The fester of defeat sharper than the], 1854—1855; nyp.00023; xxx.00048; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Poetic lines, some of which appeared slightly revised in the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass. These lines comprise part of the poem Whitman eventually titled Song of Myself. On the verso of this scrap of paper is a prose fragment in which Whitman quotes Voltaire. The prose fragment has no known connection to Whitman's published work.
- [Voices, Recitatives], 1867–1892; nyp.00036; xxx.00843; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Notes and draft lines on the "rich man's just awakened soul." The connection between this manuscript and Whitman's published work is unclear.
- Walt Whitman's Poem, 1859; nyp.00528; xxx.00849; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A draft of a notice for A Child's Reminiscence, a poem which first appeared in the 24 December 1859 issue of the New-York Saturday Press. This manuscript is catalogued with other "advance notices" of A Child's Reminiscence that do not seem to have appeared in print, though Whitman indicated with which periodical each of them would be placed. Walt Whitman's Poem appeared—as Whitman himself notes on the manuscript—"under editorial head Saturday Press Dec 24 ."
- [Then Another and very grave point], 1890–1891; nyp.00012; xxx.00560; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A partial draft of American National Literature: Is There Any Such Thing—or Can There Ever Be?, which appeared in the March 1891 issue of North American Review, as Have We a National Literature? before being collected in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ).
- Additional Note written 1887 for the English Edition., nyp.00002; xxx.00477; prose 3 leaves handwritten printed
  A nearly complete draft of an essay Whitman wrote for the English Edition of Specimen Days. This essay first appeared in 1887 as Additional Note. Written 1887 for the English Edition. Whitman slightly revised the title, changing it to Additional Note, 1887, to English Edition 'Specimen Days,' before including it in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- My own visits and distributions, 1863–1864; nyp.00060; xxx.00846; prose 4 leaves handwritten
  A draft of Civil War prose that Whitman later cannibalized and used in various published pieces about the war. Though this manuscript was not printed as a complete prose piece, it appears to be an early draft of Our Wounded and Sick Soldiers, first published in the 11 December 1864 issue of The New-York Times. Whitman reprinted parts of Our Wounded and Sick Soldiers in 'Tis But Ten Years Since, New York Weekly Graphic ( 14 February 1874, 28 February 1874, and 7 March 1874 ); in various places in Memoranda During the War ( 1876 ); and in various places in Specimen Days ( 1882 ). The verso of the final leaf contains a cancelled letter in Whitman's hand, recommending him for employment as a government clerk.